Guide to the George Moore Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Moore collection
1886-1932
GEN MSS 300
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.4
(3 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Contains letters from Moore to various people, including Jacques-Emile Blanche, Edouard Dujardin, and Edmund Gosse; manuscripts of writings by Moore, including "Esther Waters", "Heloise and Abelard", "The Nineness in the Oneness", and "The Peacock's Feathers."
Moore, George, 1852-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to George Moore, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Series I, Letters from George Moore, is housed in folders 1-38. Series II, Other Papers, includes writings and a clipping. Series III, Additions Since July 1997, contains material acquired after July 1997 and listed in accession order.
Authors, Irish -- Archives; Esther Waters; Heloise and Abelard; Nineness in the oneness; Peacock's feathers; Blanche, Jacques-Émile, 1861-1942; Dujardin, Edouard, 1861-1949; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928; Moore, George, 1852-1933
- Letters from George Moore, 1916; Series I
  - 3 TLS to Mr. Bainton, 121 Ebury Street, London, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Purchase, 1966.
  - ALS to [Jacques-Emile] Blanche, 4 Kings Bench Walk, Temple, [London], [1893] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Urges Blanche to visit Sir William
    and Lady Eden in Paris.
    Accompanied by ALS from Alfred F.
    Goldsmith to Mrs. Bernard F. Gimbel,
    1925 Jan 19.
    Gift, 1958.
  - ALS to [Jacques-Emile] Blanche, Beeding, Sussex, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift, 1977.
  - Letters to Edouard Dujardin, 1886-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4-15)
    Each letter is tipped to a sheet
    containing an English translation.
    In French.
  - Letters to Edouard Dujardin (cont.), 1914-22 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - 3 TLS to Earl E. Fisk, 121 Ebury Street, London, S.W.1, 1920-22 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Purchase, 1956.
  - ALS to Stephen Gooden, 121 Ebury Street, [1930] Apr 9 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Removed from: The Book Kerith by
    George Moore (London: W. Heinemann
    ltd., 1929).
    Gift, 1974.
  - 2 ALS to Edmund Gosse, 1893, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    With envelopes.
    Purchase, 1953.
  - 2 ALS to [Edmund] Gosse, 121 Ebury Street, [1922?] (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Dated Apr 19 and Apr 25.
    Removed from: In Single Strictness by George Moore (London, 1922).
    Purchase, 1970.
  - ALS to [Edmund] Gosse, 121 Ebury Street, Sep 12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Removed from: The Making of an Immortal by George Moore (New York:
    The Bowling Green Press, London:
    Faber & Gwyer, ltd., 1927).
  - ALS to Miss Gough, Paris, 1902 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Accompanied by signed photograph of
    Moore.
  - ALS to Miss Gough, 33 Pont Street, S.W., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Removed from: Fatal Beauty by E. V.
    Lucas (1917).
    Gift, 1951.
  - ALS to Miss Gough, Nevill Holt, Market Harboro, Medbourne, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Gift, 1969.
  - TLS to Mr. [Henry] Jowett, 121 Ebury Street, London, S.W.1., 1920 Jan 20 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Purchase, 1944.
  - ALS to Madame la Marquise Clara Lanza, S. Kings Bench Walk, Temple, [1889? Nov 23] (Box 2, Folder 27)
    With envelope.
  - ALS to [Aristide Marie], Hotel Continental, Paris, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Purchase, 1941.
  - ALS to [Linda] Porter, Hotel Continental, Paris (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Removed from: Letters from George Moore to Ed. Dujardin, 1886-1922 (New York: C. Gaige, 1929).
    Gift.
  - ALS to Frederic Prokosch, 121 Ebury Street, London, S.W.I., 1930 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Gift, 1941.
  - ANS to C. T. Scott, 121 Ebury Street, S.W., 1912 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Purchase, 1943.
  - 2 TLS to [William Kean] Seymour, 121 Ebury Street, S.W.1., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Purchase, 1975.
  - ALS to T. K. Smith, 121 Ebury Street, [1919] Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - ALS to Mr. Smith, 121 Ebury Street, [1919]
    Enclosing galley proofs, corrected,
    for "The Nineness in the Oneness."
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Portfolio
  - 2 TLS to Mr. Smith, 121 Ebury Street, London, S.W.1, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Letter of 1920 Aug 30 encloses TL
    carbon to D. Appleton & Co.
    Accompanied by proofs of part of Heloise and Abelard.
    Purchase, 1960.
  - TLS and ALS to [James] Stephens, 121 Ebury Street, 1925, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Purchase, 1942.
  - ALS to Betty Webb, Hotel Continental, Paris, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Contradicting a rumor that he was
    married.
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, 4 Upper Ely Place, Dublin, 1903 Jan 17 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Ireland (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Removed from: Pagan Poems by George
    Moore (London, 1881).
    Gift, 1943.
- Other Papers, Series II
  - WRITINGS OF GEORGE MOORE
    - "Esther Waters", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Autograph manuscript, chapter 24.
      Gift, 1961.
    - "Fragments from Heloise and Abelard", 1921 Jul (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Typescript, corrected and signed.
      Gift, 1983.
    - "The Nineness in the Oneness"
      See: Portfolio, folder 43
    - "The Peacock's Feathers: A Comedy in Three Acts", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Typescript carbon, corrected.
      Purchase, 1988.
  - NEWSPAPER CLIPPING
    - Clipping regarding Moore, 1932 Aug 6 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Additions Since July 1997, Series III
  - MOORE, GEORGE
    - "Esther Waters", [ca. 1894] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Holograph, corrected, of chapter 41.
      Headed, "Chapter 26."
      Acc: 20010309-s
    - 4 ALS and 1 TLS to Captain Henderson Bland, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      With copies of two replies and
      ALS to Colonel Longworth
      Acc: 20000201-j
    - ALS to "Dear Sir;" 121 Ebury Street, n.y. Jun 7 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Acc: 20010309-f
    - TLS to Dr. Collins; 121 Ebury Street, 1920 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Acc: 20010309-g
    - ALS to "Dear Sir;" 121 Ebury Street, [ca. 1918 Mar 22] (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Acc: 20010309-h
    - ALS to Mark Fisher; 121 Ebury Street, n.y. May 2 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Acc: 20010309-i
    - TLS (carbon) to "Dear Sir;" 121 Ebury Street, 1927 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Concerning a French translation
      of "The Brook Kerith."
      Acc: 20010309-j
    - ALS to "Dear Sir", n.y. Oct 23 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Concerning proof of a preface.
      Acc: 20010309-k
    - LS to "Mr. O'Brien"; 121 Ebury Street, 1919 Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      Concerning the American publication
      of "Avowals."
      Acc: 20010309-l
    - ALS to "Dear Sir;" 121 Ebury Street, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Concerning the return of corrected
      proofs.
      Acc: 20010309-m
    - ALS to "Dear Princess" [Amelie Rives Troubetskoy]; 92 Victoria Street, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Thanking her for a letter and
      promising to read "Virginia
      of Virginia."
      Acc: 20010309-n
    - TLS, corrected, to "Dear Sir" [Barrett Harper Clark]; 121 Ebury Street, 1915 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Concerning Clark's "Contemporary
      French Dramatists" and the postal
      service.
      Acc: 20010309-o
    - ALS to "Dear de Mattos", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Bound with reprint from the English Review of "Euphorion in Texas,"
      1914 Jul; and a reproduction of a
      lithographed portrait of Moore by
      Miss Harrison.
      Bookplate: John A. Spoor.
      Binding: three-quarter green
      morocco, by Riviere.
      Purchased in 2001.
      Acc: 20010720-e
    - The Making of an Immortal, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Galley proofs of the first edition,
      cut and mounted on blank leaves, and
      bound.
      Inscribed to Mary Hunter from GM, 1927.
      Bookplate: Mary Hunter.
      Purchased in 2002.
      Acc: 20021015-c
    - ALS to [Lena Margaret] Ashwell; 4, Upper Ely Place, Dublin, 1908 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Inviting her to lunch and mentioning
      his new comedy.
      Purchased in 2004.
      Acc: 20040825-u
    - A Story Teller's Holiday, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Second and third page proofs,
      corrected and revised.
      Signed and dated: "George Moore,
      May, 1918."
      Ex libris B. George Ulizio.
      Ex libris Donald Stralem.
- Portfolio, [1919]
  - ALS to Mr. Smith, 121 Ebury Street, [1919] (Box Portfolio, folder 43)